Guide to the Winston Weisman Collection of Architectural Photographs [1950]-1973 depicting structures ca. 1850 - 1970 PR 73
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Project Soho
  - PROJECT SOHO COPY PRINTS
    - 120 mm film prints of original architect's drawings
      - roll S: plans of 407 -- 409 West Broadway, 425 West Broadway, 555 Broadway (120 -- 126 Mercer Street) (Box 85, Folder 891)
      - roll T: plans of 555 Broadway, 15 -- 17 Mercer Street, 561 -- 563 Broadway (Box 85, Folder 892)
      - roll U: plans of 421 West Broadway, 71 Mercer Street, 78 Greene Street (Box 85, Folder 893)
      - roll V: plans of 139 -- 141 Spring Street (94 -- 98 Wooster Street), 484 -- 490 Broome Street (59 Wooster Street), 135 Wooster Street (Box 85, Folder 894)
      - roll W: plans of 135 Wooster Street, 125 Prince Street, 78 Greene Street, 80 -- 82 Wooster Street (Box 85, Folder 895)
      - roll X: plans of 149 -- 153 Wooster Street, 115 -- 121 Wooster Street, 445 -- 449 West Broadway (Box 85, Folder 896)
      - roll Y: plans of 444 Broadway, 121 Prince Street (fire escapes), 55 Grand Street, 98 Greene Street, 81 Green Street, 118 Spring Street (Box 85, Folder 897)
      - roll Z: plans of 347 West Broadway, 171 Mercer Street, 112 -- 114 Prince Street, 108 -- 114 Wooster Street (Box 85, Folder 898)
    - 35 mm film prints of original architect's drawings
      - roll AA: plans of 91 Grand Street 9 -- 13 Mercer Street 425 Broadway 444 Broadway (10 -- 12 Crosby Street) 478 -- 482 Broadway (Roosevelt Building) 483 -- 485 Broadway (56 -- 58 Mercer Street) 96 -- 102 Grand Street 461 Broome Street 457 -- 459 Broome Street 453 -- 455 Broome Street (57 -- 59 Mercer Street) 351 -- 357 Canal Street (2 -- 4 Wooster Street) 18 -- 20 Wooster Street 27 Greene Street 23 -- 25 Greene Street 27 Howard Street 269 Canal Street 365 -- 367 Canal Street 28 -- 30 Greene Street 34 Greene Street (Box 86, Folder 899)
      - roll BB: plans of 55 Mercer Street 47 -- 49 Mercer Street 489 -- 493 Broome Street 51 Wooster Street 454 Broome Street (65 -- 67 Mercer Street) 85 -- 87 Mercer Street 72 Greene Street 68 Greene Street 66 Greene Street 118 Prince Street (Box 86, Folder 900)
      - roll CC: plans of 165 -- 167 Mercer Street 147 Spring Street 367 West Broadway (500 Broome Street) 65 Greene Street (Box 86, Folder 901)
      - roll DD: plans of 269 Canal Street 425 Broadway 9 -- 13 Mercer Street 34 Greene Street 28 -- 30 Greene Street 365 -- 367 Canal Street 27 Greene Street 18 --20 Wooster Street 351 -- 357 Broadway 47 -- 49 Mercer Street 453 -- 455 Broome Street 96 -- 102 Grand Street 72 Greene Street 64 Greene Street 85 Mercer Street 454 Broome Street 65 Greene Street 367 West Broadway (500 Broome Street) 147 Spring Street (Box 86, Folder 902)
      - roll EE: plans of 163 Mercer Street 118 Prince Street 331 -- 335 West Broadway (53 Grand Street) 165 -- 67 Mercer Street 325 Canal Street uptown Stewart store (Box 86, Folder 903)
    - 120 mm film prints of building details
      - "roll HB (1)": 69 Mercer Street 478 -- 482, 486, 512, 540, 542, 550 Broadway (Box 86, Folder 904)
      - "roll HB (2)": 444, 452, 462 -- 468, 478 -- 482 Broadway (Box 86, Folder 905)
      - "roll HB (3)": 15 -- 17, 23 -- 25 Greene Street 337 -- 341 Canal Street (9 -- 13 Greene Street) 55, 57 -- 59 Mercer Street (453 -- 55 Broome Street) (Box 86, Folder 906)
      - "roll HB (4)": 70, 72 Grand Street (29, 36 -- 38 Wooster Street) 484 -- 490 Broome Street (59 Wooster Street) (Box 86, Folder 907)
      - "roll HB (5)": unidentified (Box 86, Folder 908)
      - "roll HB (6)": unidentified person at drawing board (Box 86, Folder 909)
    - Miscellaneous Project Soho prints
      - various architectural engineers' photographs broken iron reports and photographs (Box 86, Folder 910)
      - maps (Box 86, Folder 911)
      - unidentified buildings photographs and negatives (Box 86, Folder 912)
- Series V. Laing Stores Project (see also oversize)
  One of Weisman's first tasks as a commissioned consultant to the New York City Landmarks was to oversee the dismantling of the historic Laing Stores, the oldest block of cast iron in America and one of the earliest milestones of modernism, designed in 1849 by the mechanical engineer and inventor James Bogardus (1800 -- 1874). The Smithsonian Institution sponsored Weisman's photographic documentation of the event as a part of a traveling exhibition in the 1970's.
  This series consists of exhibition information and a daily journal of disassembly of the Laing Stores, made by field supervisor Benjamin Walbert. A selection of photos from eighteen rolls of film taken during the disassembly project is available in this series, as both negatives and prints.
  This series in unique in giving both a history of the design and construction of an important building in combination with its dismantling and partial reassembly, and revealing the interrelationship of brick and timber construction with the use of cast iron facades.
  The real estate on which the Laing Stores stood was turned over to the City University of New York for the projected Manhattan Community College, in exchange for which the CUNY, agreed to re-erect the Laing building within the college complex. The iron sections were placed in a storage area. This projected project was never brought to fruition. These sections were later to be part of another never begun project as part of the Washington Market Urban Renewal Project. The Bogardus Building on the South Street Seaport Museum block was then originally designed as an armature to house the cast iron components of the Laing Stores. Unfortunately, the valuable pieces were stolen for scrap metal in two incidents (1974, 1977). The Bogardus Building was built with a façade using a concept of exposed steel, an abstraction of Bogardus' original design, which inspired this new building but no longer containing any of the original ironwork of the Laing Stores.
  In 1990, Weisman donated two architectural pieces of decorative elements from the Laing Stores, designed by William L. Miller, that are located in Decorative Arts at the New-York Historical Society.
  This series is divided into two subseries: reports and prints. Housed at the end of this collection are a set of oversize mounted photographs from Weisman's Laing Stores negatives which were used in an exhibition.
  - REPORTS
    - Laing Stores Survey 1971 journal of disassembly by Benjamin Walbert copies of demolition company's daily reports (Box 87, Folder 913)
    - Disassembly of the Laing Stores preliminary report and rough draft of press releases (Box 87, Folder 914)
    - exhibition text and published brochure (Box 87, Folder 915)
  - PRINTS
    - used for Historic American Buildings Survey (Box 87, Folder 916)
    - Roll #1 -- Roll #4 (Box 87, Folder 917-920)
    - Roll #5 -- Roll #18 (Box 88, Folder 921-934)
    - miscellaneous, including shots of workmen involved in disassembly (Box 88, Folder 935)
- Series VI. Manhattan Buildings Research
  This series consists of Weisman's scrapbooks of data sheets and prints arranged in chronological order by construction date. The data sheets contain such basic information as construction costs and brief physical descriptions, as well as bibliographical notes. This research material is in files in the same order as in the Weisman's binders themselves, with the exception of the indices that have been placed in the first folder. These indices give a list year-by-year of the New York City buildings included in this series. These buildings are predominantly early skyscrapers, built 1865 -- 1897. All the photos included with the information are also located among the mounted copy prints.
  - Index, 1865 -- 1899 (Box 89, Folder 936)
  - 1863 -- 1889 (Box 89, Folder 937 - 955)
  - 1890 -- 1897 (Box 90, Folder 956 - 963)
- Series VII. Lectures and Writings
  This series is comprised of both published works and drafts of various articles and lectures produced by Dr. Weisman throughout his career. It is arranged in approximate chronological order of Weisman's expanding interests as outlined in his proposed book on the history of commercial architecture in folder 964, beginning with his dissertation on Rockefeller Center and ending with an article about preservation in the 1970's. All of his major interests are represented. There are also photographs, such as Rockefeller Center and Metropolitan Square, that correspond to articles and lectures.
  - outline for proposed book, "Selected Writings on the History of Commercial Architecture" (Box 91, Folder 964)
  - Ph.D. dissertation, "Architectural Significance of Rockefeller Center" (Box 91, Folder 965)
  - Rockefeller Center plans and drawings copy prints for dissertation and lectures, figures 1 -- 39 (Box 91, Folder 966)
  - Rockefeller Center plans and drawings copy prints for dissertation and lectures, figures 46 -- 108 (Box 91, Folder 967)
  - Rockefeller Center plans and drawings copy prints for dissertation and lectures, miscellaneous (Box 91, Folder 968)
  - History of the Skyscraper lecture schedule and list of significant buildings 1845 -- 1900, University of Pennsylvania, Spring, 1958 (Box 91, Folder 969)
  - Modern Architecture Symposium, 1966, "The Skyscraper: 1907 -- 1917" (Box 91, Folder 970)
  - lecture and list of illustrations, "Origins of the Skyscraper (in English and Italian)" (Box 91, Folder 971)
  - The Origins of the Skyscraper (rough draft) (Box 92, Folder 972)
  - New View of Skyscraper History (Box 92, Folder 973)
  - The Chicago School Issue lecture (1971) (Box 92, Folder 974)
  - photos for Prairie School article (Chicago School Issue) (Box 92, Folder 975)
  - The Early Commercial Architecture of George B. Post, rough draft, research, correspondence (Box 92, Folder 976)
  - Slab Buildings article (The Architectural Review, February, 1952) (Box 92, Folder 977)
  - Chicago elevator buildings notes, 1883 -- 1884 (Box 92, Folder 978)
  - photos of miscellaneous skyscrapers for the book The Rise of American Architecture (Metropolitan Museum) (Box 92, Folder 979)
  - History of New York Architecture article drafts (Box 92, Folder 980)
  - The Commercial Style in New York article rough draft (Box 92, Folder 981)
  - research notes on commercial architecture, predominantly from the New York Times (1874 -- 1883) (Box 92, Folder 982)
  - preservation lecture and Centre Daily Times, Stage College, PA, 1970, article (Box 92, Folder 983)
  - Remarks on Fire-Proof Construction by P.B. Wright (Box 92, Folder 984)
  - miscellaneous building photos for lecture (Box 92, Folder 985)
- Series VIII. Specific Architects Material
  This series predominantly consists of prints and negatives of buildings by specific architects, such as E. H. Kendall, Peabody and Stearns, Samuel Warner, and Alfred Zucker. These photos were taken by students of Dr. Weisman to accompany their school projects and dissertations. The series also includes photocopies of pages from Cyclopedia of American Biography on three important figures in architectural writing and history: Michael A. Mikkelsen, Montgomery Schuyler and Henry R. Towne.
  - E. H. Kendall photos - Dick Porter's dissertation (Box 93, Folder 986)
  - Peabody and Stearns pictures and list of buildings (Box 93, Folder 987)
  - Samuel Warner photos- taken by Barbara W. Jamieson (Box 93, Folder 988)
  - Alfred Zucker photos and negatives (Box 93, Folder 989)
  - miscellaneous negatives (index included) of buildings designed predominantly by A. Zucker and H. Fernbach (Box 93, Folder 990)
  - photocopies of pages of Cyclopedia of American Biography, Michael A. Mikkelsen, Montgomery Schuyler, Henry R. Towne (Box 93, Folder 991)
  - Classical America (Box 93, Folder 992)
- Series IX. Assorted Unmounted Copy Photographs
  This series consists of miscellaneous buildings, both named and unidentified, including Gradin Library in Clinton, New Jersey and buildings in St. Louis.
  - Gradin Library, Clinton, N.J. -- photos, newspaper article, letter (Box 94, Folder 993)
  - St. Louis buildings photo stats (Box 94, Folder 994)
  - miscellaneous prints -- named (Box 94, Folder 995)
  - miscellaneous prints -- unidentified (Box 94, Folder 996)
  - miscellaneous contact sheets -- Italy (Box 94, Folder 997)
  - miscellaneous architectural conceptions (Box 94, Folder 998)
- Series X. Oversize Copy Photographs
  This series consists of four approximately 9 x 14 mounted print copies of unidentified buildings.
  - miscellaneous oversize prints (Box 96, Folder 999)
- Series XI. 35 mm. Negatives
  This series consists of 35 mm rolls of film of miscellaneous buildings, predominately in Manhattan but also including Philadelphia, Boston and Chicago. A second small subseries of miscellaneous negatives includes the Weisman family and figure drawings. Prints and negatives of the images of the buildings are also available in Series I, II, and IV.
  - BUILDINGS
    - Manhattan, New York -- photographed by Winston Weisman, 1960 (Box 96, Folder 1000)
    - Manhattan, New York -- from miscellaneous books and magazines (Box 96, Folder 1001)
    - images from Deleeuw Views of Broadway (Box 96, Folder 1002)
    - images from King's Views of New York (Box 96, Folder 1003)
    - Baltimore, MD and Rhode Island (Box 96, Folder 1004)
    - Boston, MA (Box 96, Folder 1005)
    - Chicago, IL (Box 96, Folder 1006)
    - Philadelphia, PA (Box 96, Folder 1007)
    - Philadelphia, PA -- images from Weisman's functionalism article (Box 96, Folder 1008)
    - United Kingdom (Box 96, Folder 1009)
    - miscellaneous architectural photographs --from books (Box 96, Folder 1010)
    - images from Architectural Record (Box 96, Folder 1011)
    - images from Avery Index to Architectural Periodicals (Box 96, Folder 1012)
    - images from Badger's Illustrated Catalogue of Cast-Iron Archicture by Daniel D. Badger (Box 96, Folder 1013)
    - images from History of the Skyscraper by Franciso Mujica (Box 96, Folder 1014)
    - images of Church plans -- from an unidentified German book (Box 96, Folder 1015)
    - images of medieval iconography and coins (Box 96, Folder 1016)
  - MISCELLANEOUS
    - images of figure drawings (Box 96, Folder 1017)
    - Weisman family photograph (Box 96, Folder 1018)
- Oversize
  - prints from Laing Stores Project exhibition (Box 97-98)
  - Maps of Soho historic district (Box 99-100)
    Provenance note
    These maps may not have been part of the original collection